### DANIEL MUELLER

630-452-1477 demuelle@gmail.com

#### SUMMARY

Analytical, collaborative software development professional and leader, with experience in application development on a Linux platform using multiple programming and scripting languages. Strong problem-solving skills with a drive to build elegant, performant, supportable, and maintainable software. Enthusiastic written and verbal communicator, and mentor, with a reputation for dependable delivery, and individual and team success.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Trilogy Education, a 2U, Inc. brand, Chicago, IL

2019 to present

2U powers the world's best digital higher education.

# **Enterprise Instructor**

2019 to present

Lectured to, mentored, monitored, motivated, opined to, supported, encouraged, and amused the classroom during challenging technical boot camp programs aimed at preparing learners for a full-time software development role.

- Administered course as lead instructor for three cohorts.
- Wrote 25 scripts for videos that are used as asynchronous content in the full stack (MERN) curriculum.
- Mentored other instructors as the facilitator of weekly program-specific office hours.
- Generated and refined supporting content to be used with enterprise curriculum.

Java - Southern Methodist University

May - Jul 2021

Feb - May 2021

Sep - Dec 2019

May - Jul 2019

Java - Northwestern University

Prepared learners for employment with an enterprise partner. Course curriculum includes java programming language fundamentals, test driven development, spring boot, API development, microservice architecture and related technologies, and agile methodology.

Data Science and Visualization (part-time) – Northwestern University Sep 2020 – Feb 2021 Curriculum includes VBA for Excel, Python, Pandas, JavaScript, MongoDB, Machine Learning, and more.

Full Stack Development (full-time) – University of Minnesota Full Stack Development (part-time) – University of Denver

Sep - Dec 2020

Jan - Jul 2020

Curriculum includes HTML, CSS, bootstrap, JavaScript, jQuery, Node.JS, React, MySQL, MongoDB, and more.

ShopperTrak, Chicago, IL

2007 to 2019

World leader in brick-and-mortar customer behavior analytics.

**Senior Manager, Software Development** 

2016 to 2019

D. Mueller Page Two

Directed multiple teams in the development, expansion, and enhancement of externally facing web applications and application programming interfaces.

- Managed 10 full-time employees and 15 contractors on 4 continents, who built, tested, and delivered software and data for ShopperTrak's portfolio of 1000+ corporate customers.
- Worked with internal and external customers to vet requirements for products and pilots.
- Interviewed, hired, mentored, directed, and evaluated employees and contractors.

# **Senior Software Engineer**

2007 to 2016

Lead multiple teams in the development, expansion, and enhancement of both internal and external customer facing web applications and application programming interfaces.

- Lead development and acted as product owner of the most widely used analytics platform at ShopperTrak – Insights, which serves 388 customers and 22000 users (java 7, spring framework, jasper reports, PL/SQL, ibatis, jsp, quartz scheduler)
- Designed and developed the main internal support application Operations Portal which is used by 80 internal users to support 60000 global devices.
- Served as subject matter expert of data acquisition on the most widely used method of connecting to traffic counter devices – single site connectivity, which is the most reliable and preferred Internet of Things connectivity type offered by ShopperTrak
- Lead project to migrate authentication and user administration for 13 applications off of a non-portable version of Idap to a custom-built authentication and authorization RESTful API.
- Refactored implementation of real-time reporting user interface to reduce load on architecture, and improve responsiveness by 90% on initial load.
- Interfaced with internal and external stakeholders, including customer business, technical, and operational contacts, vendors, sales, finance, engagement, professional services, and operations.
- Mentored new hires on technical matters, processes, practices, benefits, and organizational structures.

#### TERADYNE, Inc., Broadband Test Division, Deerfield, IL 2000 to 2006

A leader and innovator in single ended testing of copper telephone lines, focusing on fault identification and digital subscriber line (DSL) service qualification.

## **Customer Applications Engineer**

Developed custom applications built on telephone line test platform for 7 customers; Interfaced with external and internal customers to understand needs, requirements, and constraints; Investigated and resolved system defects

- Reduced product turn-up time from 9 months to 3 months by developing a flexible, customized batch testing interface solution.
- Reduced the cost of test head calibration by 90% with the development of an automated process for data collection and analysis.
- Integrated support for Cisco routers into core software as a reliable communications server.

D. Mueller Page Two

### **EDUCATION**

BS in Computer Engineering, University of Illinois, Urbana, IL, 2000

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

Sun Certified Java Programmer, 2005

# **PUBLICATIONS AND PATENTS**

Patent (filed 12/29/2005) Afzal, M., Mueller, D., Alamo, A. - "Automatic Provisioning of a Telephone Line Test System"

Word Hacks, Tips & Tools for Taming Your Text by Andrew Savikas, Contributor

# LANGUAGES, SKILLS, TOOLS, FRAMEWORKS

Java, SQL, JavaScript, Node.js/Express, React, jQuery, Jenkins, bash, Linux, spring boot, spring framework, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, IntelliJ IDEA, git